An Historical Sketch of the Progress of Opinion on the Origin of Species, Previously to the Publication of the First Edition of This Work

I will here give a brief sketch of the progress of opinion on the Origin of Species. Until recently the great majority of naturalists believed that species were immutable productions, and had been separately created. This view has been ably maintained by many authors. Some few naturalists, on the other hand, have believed that species undergo modification, and that the existing forms of life are the descendants by true generation of preexisting forms. Passing over allusions to the subject in the classical writers,[1] the first author who in modern times has treated it in a scientific spirit was Buffon. But as his opinions fluctuated greatly at different periods, and as he does not enter on the causes or means of the transformation of species, I need not here enter on details.

Lamarck was the first man whose conclusions on the subject excited much attention. This justly celebrated naturalist first published his views in 1801; he much enlarged them in 1809 in his “Philosophie Zoologique,” and subsequently, 1815, in the Introduction to his Hist. Nat. des Animaux sans Vertebres. In these works he upholds the doctrine that all species, including man, are descended from other species. He first did the eminent service of arousing attention to the probability of all change in the organic, as well as in the inorganic world, being the result of law, and not of miraculous interposition. Lamarck seems to have been chiefly led to his conclusion on the gradual change of species, by the difficulty of distinguishing species and varieties, by the almost perfect gradation of forms in certain groups, and by the analogy of domestic productions. With respect to the means of modification, he attributed something to the direct action of the physical conditions of life, something to the crossing of already existing forms, and much to use and disuse, that is, to the effects of habit. To this latter agency he seems to attribute all the beautiful adaptations in nature; such as the long neck of the giraffe for browsing on the branches of trees. But he likewise believed in a law of progressive development, and as all the forms of life thus tend to progress, in order to account for the existence at the present day of simple productions, he maintains that such forms are now spontaneously generated.[2]

Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, as is stated in his Life, written by his son, suspected, as early as 1795, that what we call species are various degenerations of the same type. It was not until 1828 that he published his conviction that the same forms have not been perpetuated since the origin of all things. Geoffroy seems to have relied chiefly on the conditions of life, or the monde ambiant as the cause of change. He was cautious in drawing conclusions, and did not believe that existing species are now undergoing modification; and, as his son adds, “C’est donc un probleme a reserver entierement a l’avenir, suppose meme que l’avenir doive avoir prise sur lui.”

In 1813 Dr. W. C. Wells read before the Royal Society “An Account of a White Female, part of whose skin resembles that of a Negro;” but his paper was not published until his famous Two Essays upon Dew and Single Vision appeared in 1818. In this paper he distinctly recognises the principle of natural selection, and this is the first recognition which has been indicated; but he applies it only to the races of man, and to certain characters alone. After remarking that negroes and mulattoes enjoy an immunity from certain tropical diseases, he observes, firstly, that all animals tend to vary in some degree, and, secondly, that agriculturists improve their domesticated animals by selection; and then, he adds, but what is done in this latter case “by art, seems to be done with equal efficacy, though more slowly, by nature, in the formation of varieties of mankind, fitted for the country which they inhabit. Of the accidental varieties of man, which would occur among the first few and scattered inhabitants of the middle regions of Africa, some one would be better fitted than others to bear the diseases of the country. This race would consequently multiply, while the others would decrease; not only from their inability to sustain the attacks of disease, but from their incapacity of contending with their more vigorous neighbours. The colour of this vigorous race I take for granted, from what has been already said, would be dark. But the same disposition to form varieties still existing, a darker and a darker race would in the course of time occur: and as the darkest would be the best fitted for the climate, this would at length become the most prevalent, if not the only race, in the particular country in which it had originated.” He then extends these same views to the white inhabitants of colder climates. I am indebted to Mr. Rowley, of the United States, for having called my attention, through Mr. Brace, to the above passage of Dr. Wells’ work.

The Hon. and Rev. W. Herbert, afterward Dean of Manchester, in the fourth volume of the Horticultural Transactions, 1822, and in his work on the Amaryllidaceae (1837, pages 19, 339), declares that “horticultural experiments have established, beyond the possibility of refutation, that botanical species are only a higher and more permanent class of varieties.” He extends the same view to animals. The dean believes that single species of each genus were created in an originally highly plastic condition, and that these have produced, chiefly by inter-crossing, but likewise by variation, all our existing species.

In 1826 Professor Grant, in the concluding paragraph in his well-known paper (Edinburgh Philosophical Journal, vol. XIV, page 283) on the Spongilla, clearly declares his belief that species are descended from other species, and that they become improved in the course of modification. This same view was given in his Fifty-fifth Lecture, published in the Lancet in 1834.

In 1831 Mr. Patrick Matthew published his work on Naval Timber and Arboriculture, in which he gives precisely the same view on the origin of species as that (presently to be alluded to) propounded by Mr. Wallace and myself in the Linnean Journal, and as that enlarged in the present volume. Unfortunately the view was given by Mr. Matthew very briefly in scattered passages in an appendix to a work on a different subject, so that it remained unnoticed until Mr. Matthew himself drew attention to it in the Gardeners’ Chronicle, on April 7, 1860. The differences of Mr. Matthew’s views from mine are not of much importance: he seems to consider that the world was nearly depopulated at successive periods, and then restocked; and he gives as an alternative, that new forms may be generated “without the presence of any mold or germ of former aggregates.” I am not sure that I understand some passages; but it seems that he attributes much influence to the direct action of the conditions of life. He clearly saw, however, the full force of the principle of natural selection.

The celebrated geologist and naturalist, Von Buch, in his excellent Description Physique des Isles Canaries (1836, page 147), clearly expresses his belief that varieties slowly become changed into permanent species, which are no longer capable of intercrossing.

Rafinesque, in his New Flora of North America, published in 1836, wrote (page 6) as follows: “All species might have been varieties once, and many varieties are gradually becoming species by assuming constant and peculiar characters;” but further on (page 18) he adds, “except the original types or ancestors of the genus.”

In 1843–44 Professor Haldeman (Boston Journal of Nat. Hist. U. States, vol. iv, page 468) has ably given the arguments for and against the hypothesis of the development and modification of species: he seems to lean toward the side of change.

The Vestiges of Creation appeared in 1844. In the tenth and much improved edition (1853) the anonymous author says (page 155): “The proposition determined on after much consideration is, that the several series of animated beings, from the simplest and oldest up to the highest and most recent, are, under the providence of God, the results, first, of an impulse which has been imparted to the forms of life, advancing them, in definite times, by generation, through grades of organisation terminating in the highest dicotyledons and vertebrata, these grades being few in number, and generally marked by intervals of organic character, which we find to be a practical difficulty in ascertaining affinities; second, of another impulse connected with the vital forces, tending, in the course of generations, to modify organic structures in accordance with external circumstances, as food, the nature of the habitat, and the meteoric agencies, these being the ‘adaptations’ of the natural theologian.” The author apparently believes that organisation progresses by sudden leaps, but that the effects produced by the conditions of life are gradual. He argues with much force on general grounds that species are not immutable productions. But I cannot see how the two supposed “impulses” account in a scientific sense for the numerous and beautiful coadaptations which we see throughout nature; I cannot see that we thus gain any insight how, for instance, a woodpecker has become adapted to its peculiar habits of life. The work, from its powerful and brilliant style, though displaying in the early editions little accurate knowledge and a great want of scientific caution, immediately had a very wide circulation. In my opinion it has done excellent service in this country in calling attention to the subject, in removing prejudice, and in thus preparing the ground for the reception of analogous views.

In 1846 the veteran geologist M. J. d’Omalius d’Halloy published in an excellent though short paper (Bulletins de l’Acad. Roy. Bruxelles, tom. xiii, page 581) his opinion that it is more probable that new species have been produced by descent with modification than that they have been separately created: the author first promulgated this opinion in 1831.

Professor Owen, in 1849 (Nature of Limbs, page 86), wrote as follows: “The archetypal idea was manifested in the flesh under diverse such modifications, upon this planet, long prior to the existence of those animal species that actually exemplify it. To what natural laws or secondary causes the orderly succession and progression of such organic phenomena may have been committed, we, as yet, are ignorant.” In his address to the British Association, in 1858, he speaks (page li) of “the axiom of the continuous operation of creative power, or of the ordained becoming of living things.” Further on (page xc), after referring to geographical distribution, he adds, “These phenomena shake our confidence in the conclusion that the Apteryx of New Zealand and the Red Grouse of England were distinct creations in and for those islands respectively. Always, also, it may be well to bear in mind that by the word ‘creation’ the zoologist means ‘a process he knows not what.’ ” He amplifies this idea by adding that when such cases as that of the Red Grouse are “enumerated by the zoologist as evidence of distinct creation of the bird in and for such islands, he chiefly expresses that he knows not how the Red Grouse came to be there, and there exclusively; signifying also, by this mode of expressing such ignorance, his belief that both the bird and the islands owed their origin to a great first Creative Cause.” If we interpret these sentences given in the same address, one by the other, it appears that this eminent philosopher felt in 1858 his confidence shaken that the Apteryx and the Red Grouse first appeared in their respective homes “he knew not how,” or by some process “he knew not what.”

This address was delivered after the papers by Mr. Wallace and myself on the Origin of Species, presently to be referred to, had been read before the Linnean Society. When the first edition of this work was published, I was so completely deceived, as were many others, by such expressions as “the continuous operation of creative power,” that I included Professor Owen with other palaeontologists as being firmly convinced of the immutability of species; but it appears (Anat. of Vertebrates, vol. iii, page 796) that this was on my part a preposterous error. In the last edition of this work I inferred, and the inference still seems to me perfectly just, from a passage beginning with the words “no doubt the type-form,” etc.(Ibid., vol. i, page xxxv), that Professor Owen admitted that natural selection may have done something in the formation of a new species; but this it appears (Ibid., vol. iii page 798) is inaccurate and without evidence. I also gave some extracts from a correspondence between Professor Owen and the editor of the London Review, from which it appeared manifest to the editor as well as to myself, that Professor Owen claimed to have promulgated the theory of natural selection before I had done so; and I expressed my surprise and satisfaction at this announcement; but as far as it is possible to understand certain recently published passages (Ibid., vol. iii page 798) I have either partially or wholly again fallen into error. It is consolatory to me that others find Professor Owen’s controversial writings as difficult to understand and to reconcile with each other, as I do. As far as the mere enunciation of the principle of natural selection is concerned, it is quite immaterial whether or not Professor Owen preceded me, for both of us, as shown in this historical sketch, were long ago preceded by Dr. Wells and Mr. Matthews.

M. Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire, in his lectures delivered in 1850 (of which a Resume appeared in the Revue et Mag. de Zoolog., Jan., 1851), briefly gives his reason for believing that specific characters “sont fixes, pour chaque espece, tant qu’elle se perpetue au milieu des memes circonstances: ils se modifient, si les circonstances ambiantes viennent a changer. En resume, L’observation des animaux sauvages demontre deja la variabilite limitee des especes. Les experiences sur les animaux sauvages devenus domestiques, et sur les animaux domestiques redevenus sauvages, la demontrent plus clairment encore. Ces memes experiences prouvent, de plus, que les differences produites peuvent etre de valeur generique.” In his Hist. Nat. Generale (tom. ii, page 430, 1859) he amplifies analogous conclusions.

From a circular lately issued it appears that Dr. Freke, in 1851 (Dublin Medical Press, page 322), propounded the doctrine that all organic beings have descended from one primordial form. His grounds of belief and treatment of the subject are wholly different from mine; but as Dr. Freke has now (1861) published his essay on the Origin of Species by means of Organic Affinity, the difficult attempt to give any idea of his views would be superfluous on my part.

Mr. Herbert Spencer, in an essay (originally published in the Leader, March, 1852, and republished in his Essays, in 1858), has contrasted the theories of the creation and the development of organic beings with remarkable skill and force. He argues from the analogy of domestic productions, from the changes which the embryos of many species undergo, from the difficulty of distinguishing species and varieties, and from the principle of general gradation, that species have been modified; and he attributes the modification to the change of circumstances. The author (1855) has also treated psychology on the principle of the necessary acquirement of each mental power and capacity by gradation.

In 1852 M. Naudin, a distinguished botanist, expressly stated, in an admirable paper on the Origin of Species (Revue Horticole, page 102; since partly republished in the Nouvelles Archives du Museum, tom. i, page 171), his belief that species are formed in an analogous manner as varieties are under cultivation; and the latter process he attributes to man’s power of selection. But he does not show how selection acts under nature. He believes, like Dean Herbert, that species, when nascent, were more plastic than at present. He lays weight on what he calls the principle of finality, “puissance mysterieuse, indeterminee; fatalite pour les uns; pour les autres volonte providentielle, dont l’action incessante sur les etres vivantes determine, a toutes les epoques de l’existence du monde, la forme, le volume, et la duree de chacun d’eux, en raison de sa destinee dans l’ordre de choses dont il fait partie. C’est cette puissance qui harmonise chaque membre a l’ensemble, en l’appropriant à la fonction qu’il doit remplir dans l’organisme general de la nature, fonction qui est pour lui sa raison d’etre.”[3]

In 1853 a celebrated geologist, Count Keyserling (Bulletin de la Soc. Geolog., 2nd Ser., tom. x, page 357), suggested that as new diseases, supposed to have been caused by some miasma have arisen and spread over the world, so at certain periods the germs of existing species may have been chemically affected by circumambient molecules of a particular nature, and thus have given rise to new forms.

In this same year, 1853, Dr. Schaaffhausen published an excellent pamphlet (Verhand. des Naturhist. Vereins der Preuss. Rheinlands, etc.), in which he maintains the development of organic forms on the earth. He infers that many species have kept true for long periods, whereas a few have become modified. The distinction of species he explains by the destruction of intermediate graduated forms. “Thus living plants and animals are not separated from the extinct by new creations, but are to be regarded as their descendants through continued reproduction.”

A well-known French botanist, M. Lecoq, writes in 1854 (Etudes sur Geograph Bot. tom. i, page 250), “On voit que nos recherches sur la fixite ou la variation de l’espece, nous conduisent directement aux idees emises par deux hommes justement celebres, Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire et Goethe.” Some other passages scattered through M. Lecoq’s large work make it a little doubtful how far he extends his views on the modification of species.

The “Philosophy of Creation” has been treated in a masterly manner by the Rev. Baden Powell, in his Essays on the Unity of Worlds, 1855. Nothing can be more striking than the manner in which he shows that the introduction of new species is “a regular, not a casual phenomenon,” or, as Sir John Herschel expresses it, “a natural in contradistinction to a miraculous process.”

The third volume of the Journal of the Linnean Society contains papers, read July 1, 1858, by Mr. Wallace and myself, in which, as stated in the introductory remarks to this volume, the theory of natural selection is promulgated by Mr. Wallace with admirable force and clearness.

Von Baer, toward whom all zoologists feel so profound a respect, expressed about the year 1859 (see Prof. Rudolph Wagner, Zoologisch-Anthropologische Untersuchungen, 1861, s. 51) his conviction, chiefly grounded on the laws of geographical distribution, that forms now perfectly distinct have descended from a single parent-form.

In June, 1859, Professor Huxley gave a lecture before the Royal Institution on the “Persistent Types of Animal Life.” Referring to such cases, he remarks, “It is difficult to comprehend the meaning of such facts as these, if we suppose that each species of animal and plant, or each great type of organisation, was formed and placed upon the surface of the globe at long intervals by a distinct act of creative power; and it is well to recollect that such an assumption is as unsupported by tradition or revelation as it is opposed to the general analogy of nature. If, on the other hand, we view “Persistent Types” in relation to that hypothesis which supposes the species living at any time to be the result of the gradual modification of preexisting species, a hypothesis which, though unproven, and sadly damaged by some of its supporters, is yet the only one to which physiology lends any countenance; their existence would seem to show that the amount of modification which living beings have undergone during geological time is but very small in relation to the whole series of changes which they have suffered.”

In December, 1859, Dr. Hooker published his Introduction to the Australian Flora. In the first part of this great work he admits the truth of the descent and modification of species, and supports this doctrine by many original observations.

The first edition of this work was published on November 24, 1859, and the second edition on January 7, 1860.

Endnotes

Aristotle, in his Physicae Auscultationes (lib.2, cap.8, s.2), after remarking that rain does not fall in order to make the corn grow, any more than it falls to spoil the farmer’s corn when threshed out of doors, applies the same argument to organisation; and adds (as translated by Mr. Clair Grece, who first pointed out the passage to me), “So what hinders the different parts (of the body) from having this merely accidental relation in nature? as the teeth, for example, grow by necessity, the front ones sharp, adapted for dividing, and the grinders flat, and serviceable for masticating the food; since they were not made for the sake of this, but it was the result of accident. And in like manner as to other parts in which there appears to exist an adaptation to an end. Wheresoever, therefore, all things together (that is all the parts of one whole) happened like as if they were made for the sake of something, these were preserved, having been appropriately constituted by an internal spontaneity; and whatsoever things were not thus constituted, perished and still perish.” We here see the principle of natural selection shadowed forth, but how little Aristotle fully comprehended the principle, is shown by his remarks on the formation of the teeth. ↩

I have taken the date of the first publication of Lamarck from Isidore Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire’s (Hist. Nat. Générale, tom. ii page 405, 1859) excellent history of opinion on this subject. In this work a full account is given of Buffon’s conclusions on the same subject. It is curious how largely my grandfather, Dr. Erasmus Darwin, anticipated the views and erroneous grounds of opinion of Lamarck in his “Zoonomia” (vol. i pages 500–510), published in 1794. According to Isid. Geoffroy there is no doubt that Goethe was an extreme partisan of similar views, as shown in the introduction to a work written in 1794 and 1795, but not published till long afterward; he has pointedly remarked (“Goethe als Naturforscher,” von Dr. Karl Meding, s. 34) that the future question for naturalists will be how, for instance, cattle got their horns and not for what they are used. It is rather a singular instance of the manner in which similar views arise at about the same time, that Goethe in Germany, Dr. Darwin in England, and Geoffroy Saint-Hilaire (as we shall immediately see) in France, came to the same conclusion on the origin of species, in the years 1794–5. ↩

From references in Bronn’s Untersuchungen uber die Entwickelungs-Gesetze, it appears that the celebrated botanist and palaeontologist Unger published, in 1852, his belief that species undergo development and modification. Dalton, likewise, in Pander and Dalton’s work on Fossil Sloths, expressed, in 1821, a similar belief. Similar views have, as is well known, been maintained by Oken in his mystical Natur-Philosophie. From other references in Godron’s work Sur l’Espece, it seems that Bory St. Vincent, Burdach, Poiret and Fries, have all admitted that new species are continually being produced. I may add, that of the thirty-four authors named in this Historical Sketch, who believe in the modification of species, or at least disbelieve in separate acts of creation, twenty-seven have written on special branches of natural history or geology. ↩

Glossary of the Principal Scientific Terms Used in the Present Volume

(I am indebted to the kindness of Mr. W. S. Dallas for this Glossary, which has been given because several readers have complained to me that some of the terms used were unintelligible to them. Mr. Dallas has endeavoured to give the explanations of the terms in as popular a form as possible.)

Aberrant

Forms or groups of animals or plants which deviate in important characters from their nearest allies, so as not to be easily included in the same group with them, are said to be aberrant.

Aberration (in Optics)

In the refraction of light by a convex lens the rays passing through different parts of the lens are brought to a focus at slightly different distance: this is called Spherical Aberration; at the same time the coloured rays are separated by the prismatic action of the lens and likewise brought to a focus at different distance: this is Chromatic Aberration.

Abnormal

Contrary to the general rule.

Aborted

An organ is said to be aborted, when its development has been arrested at a very early stage.

Albinism

Albinos are animals in which the usual colouring matters characteristic of the species have not been produced in the skin and its appendages. Albinism is the state of being an albino.

Algae

A class of plants including the ordinary seaweeds and the filamentous freshwater weeds.

Alternation of Generations

This term is applied to a peculiar mode of reproduction which prevails among many of the lower animals, in which the egg produces a living form quite different from its parent, but from which the parent-form is reproduced by a process of budding, or by the division of the substance of the first product of the egg.

Ammonites

A group of fossil, spiral, chambered shells, allied to the existing pearly Nautilus, but having the partitions between the chambers waved in complicated patterns at their junction with the outer wall of the shell.

Analogy

That resemblance of structures which depends upon similarity of function, as in the wings of insects and birds. Such structures are said to be Analogous, and to be Analogues of each other.

Animalcule

A minute animal: generally applied to those visible only by the microscope.

Annelids

A class of worms in which the surface of the body exhibits a more or less distinct division into rings or segments, generally provided with appendages for locomotion and with gills. It includes the ordinary marine worms, the earthworms, and the leeches.

Antennae

Jointed organs appended to the head in Insects, Crustacea and Centipedes, and not belonging to the mouth.

Anthers

The summits of the stamens of flowers, in which the pollen or fertilising dust is produced.

Aplacentalia
Aplacentata
Aplacental Mammals

See Mammalia.

Archetypal

Of or belonging to the Archetype, or ideal primitive form upon which all the beings of a group seem to be organised.

Articulata

A great division of the Animal Kingdom characterised generally by having the surface of the body divided into rings called segments, a greater or less number of which are furnished with jointed legs (such as Insects, Crustaceans and Centipedes).

Asymmetrical

Having the two sides unlike.

Atrophied

Arrested in development at a very early stage.

Balanus

The genus including the common Acorn-shells which live in abundance on the rocks of the seacoast.

Batrachians

A class of animals allied to the Reptiles, but undergoing a peculiar metamorphosis, in which the young animal is generally aquatic and breathes by gills. (Examples, Frogs, Toads, and Newts.)

Boulders

Large transported blocks of stone generally embedded in clays or gravels.

Brachiopoda

A class of marine Mollusca, or soft-bodied animals, furnished with a bivalve shell, attached to submarine objects by a stalk which passes through an aperture in one of the valves, and furnished with fringed arms, by the action of which food is carried to the mouth.

Branchiae

Gills or organs for respiration in water.

Branchial

Pertaining to gills or branchiae.

Cambrian System

A series of very ancient Palaeozoic rocks, between the Laurentian and the Silurian. Until recently these were regarded as the oldest fossiliferous rocks.

Canidae

The Dog-family, including the Dog, Wolf, Fox, Jackal, etc.

Carapace

The shell enveloping the anterior part of the body in Crustaceans generally; applied also to the hard shelly pieces of the Cirripedes.

Carboniferous

This term is applied to the great formation which includes, among other rocks, the coal-measures. It belongs to the oldest, or Palaeozoic, system of formations.

Caudal

Of or belonging to the tail.

Cephalopods

The highest class of the Mollusca, or soft-bodied animals, characterised by having the mouth surrounded by a greater or less number of fleshy arms or tentacles, which, in most living species, are furnished with sucking-cups. (Examples, Cuttlefish, Nautilus.)

Cetacea

An order of Mammalia, including the Whales, Dolphins, etc., having the form of the body fish-like, the skin naked, and only the fore limbs developed.

Chelonia

An order of Reptiles including the Turtles, Tortoises, etc.

Cirripedes

An order of Crustaceans including the Barnacles and Acorn-shells. Their young resemble those of many other Crustaceans in form; but when mature they are always attached to other objects, either directly or by means of a stalk, and their bodies are enclosed by a calcareous shell composed of several pieces, two of which can open to give issue to a bunch of curled, jointed tentacles, which represent the limbs.

Coccus

The genus of Insects including the Cochineal. In these the male is a minute, winged fly, and the female generally a motionless, berrylike mass.

Cocoon

A case usually of silky material, in which insects are frequently enveloped during the second or resting-stage (pupa) of their existence. The term “cocoon-stage” is here used as equivalent to “pupa-stage.”

Coelospermous

A term applied to those fruits of the Umbelliferae which have the seed hollowed on the inner face.

Coleoptera

Beetles, an order of Insects, having a biting mouth and the first pair of wings more or less horny, forming sheaths for the second pair, and usually meeting in a straight line down the middle of the back.

Column

A peculiar organ in the flowers of Orchids, in which the stamens, style and stigma (or the reproductive parts) are united.

Compositae
Compositous Plants

Plants in which the inflorescence consists of numerous small flowers (florets) brought together into a dense head, the base of which is enclosed by a common envelope. (Examples, the Daisy, Dandelion, etc.)

Confervae

The filamentous weeds of fresh water.

Conglomerate

A rock made up of fragments of rock or pebbles, cemented together by some other material.

Corolla

The second envelope of a flower usually composed of coloured, leaf-like organs (petals), which may be united by their edges either in the basal part or throughout.

Correlation

The normal coincidence of one phenomenon, character, etc., with another.

Corymb

A bunch of flowers in which those springing from the lower part of the flower stalks are supported on long stalks so as to be nearly on a level with the upper ones.

Cotyledons

The first or seed-leaves of plants.

Crustaceans

A class of articulated animals, having the skin of the body generally more or less hardened by the deposition of calcareous matter, breathing by means of gills. (Examples, Crab, Lobster, Shrimp, etc.)

Curculio

The old generic term for the Beetles known as Weevils, characterised by their four-jointed feet, and by the head being produced into a sort of beak, upon the sides of which the antennae are inserted.

Cutaneous

Of or belonging to the skin.

Degradation

The wearing down of land by the action of the sea or of meteoric agencies.

Denudation

The wearing away of the surface of the land by water.

Devonian System
Devonian Formation

A series of Palaeozoic rocks, including the Old Red Sandstone.

Dicotyledons
Dicotyledonous Plants

A class of plants characterised by having two seed-leaves, by the formation of new wood between the bark and the old wood (exogenous growth) and by the reticulation of the veins of the leaves. The parts of the flowers are generally in multiples of five.

Differentation

The separation or discrimination of parts or organs which in simpler forms of life are more or less united.

Dimorphic

Having two distinct forms: Dimorphism is the condition of the appearance of the same species under two dissimilar forms.

Dioecious

Having the organs of the sexes upon distinct individuals.

Diorite

A peculiar form of Greenstone.

Dorsal

Of or belonging to the back.

Edentata

A peculiar order of Quadrupeds, characterised by the absence of at least the middle incisor (front) teeth in both jaws. (Examples, the Sloths and Armadillos.)

Elytra

The hardened forewings of Beetles, serving as sheaths for the membranous hind-wings, which constitute the true organs of flight.

Embryo

The young animal undergoing development within the egg or womb.

Embryology

The study of the development of the embryo.

Endemic

Peculiar to a given locality.

Entomostraca

A division of the class Crustacea, having all the segments of the body usually distinct, gills attached to the feet or organs of the mouth, and the feet fringed with fine hairs. They are generally of small size.

Eocene

The earliest of the three divisions of the Tertiary epoch of geologists. Rocks of this age contain a small proportion of shells identical with species now living.

Ephemerous Insects

Insects allied to the Mayfly.

Fauna

The totality of the animals naturally inhabiting a certain country or region, or which have lived during a given geological period.

Felidae

The Cat-family.

Feral

Having become wild from a state of cultivation or domestication.

Flora

The totality of the plants growing naturally in a country, or during a given geological period.

Florets

Flowers imperfectly developed in some respects, and collected into a dense spike or head, as in the Grasses, the Dandelion, etc.

Foetal

Of or belonging to the foetus, or embryo in course of development.

Foraminifera

A class of animals of very low organisation and generally of small size, having a jellylike body, from the surface of which delicate filaments can be given off and retracted for the prehension of external objects, and having a calcareous or sandy shell, usually divided into chambers and perforated with small apertures.

Fossiliferous

Containing fossils.

Fossorial

Having a faculty of digging. The Fossorial Hymenoptera are a group of Wasp-like Insects, which burrow in sandy soil to make nests for their young.

Frenum

(pl. Frena): A small band or fold of skin.

Fungi

(sing. Fungus): A class of cellular plants, of which Mushrooms, Toadstools, and Moulds, are familiar examples.

Furcula

The forked bone formed by the union of the collarbones in many birds, such as the common Fowl.

Gallinaceous Birds

An order of birds of which the common Fowl, Turkey, and Pheasant, are well-known examples.

Gallus

The genus of birds which includes the common Fowl.

Ganglion

A swelling or knot from which nerves are given off as from a centre.

Ganoid Fishes

Fishes covered with peculiar enamelled bony scales. Most of them are extinct.

Germinal Vesicle

A minute vesicle in the eggs of animals, from which the development of the embryo proceeds.

Glacial Period

A period of great cold and of enormous extension of ice upon the surface of the earth. It is believed that glacial periods have occurred repeatedly during the geological history of the earth, but the term is generally applied to the close of the Tertiary epoch, when nearly the whole of Europe was subjected to an arctic climate.

Gland

An organ which secretes or separates some peculiar product from the blood or sap of animals or plants.

Glottis

The opening of the windpipe into the oesophagus or gullet.

Gneiss

A rock approaching granite in composition, but more or less laminated, and really produced by the alteration of a sedimentary deposit after its consolidation.

Grallatores

The so-called wading-birds (storks, cranes, snipes, etc.), which are generally furnished with long legs, bare of feathers above the heel, and have no membranes between the toes.

Granite

A rock consisting essentially of crystals of felspar and mica in a mass of quartz.

Habitat

The locality in which a plant or animal naturally lives.

Hemiptera

An order or suborder of insects, characterised by the possession of a jointed beak or rostrum, and by having the forewings horny in the basal portion and membranous at the extremity, where they cross each other. This group includes the various species of bugs.

Hermaphrodite

Possessing the organs of both sexes.

Homology

That relation between parts which results from their development from corresponding embryonic parts, either in different animals, as in the case of the arm of man, the foreleg of a quadruped, and the wing of a bird; or in the same individual, as in the case of the fore and hind legs in quadrupeds, and the segments or rings and their appendages of which the body of a worm, a centipede, etc., is composed. The latter is called serial homology. The parts which stand in such a relation to each other are said to be homologous, and one such part or organ is called the homologue of the other. In different plants the parts of the flower are homologous, and in general these parts are regarded as homologous with leaves.

Homoptera

An order or suborder of insects having (like the Hemiptera) a jointed beak, but in which the forewings are either wholly membranous or wholly leathery. The Cicadae, froghoppers, and Aphides, are well-known examples.

Hybrid

The offspring of the union of two distinct species.

Hymenoptera

An order of insects possessing biting jaws and usually four membranous wings in which there are a few veins. Bees and wasps are familiar examples of this group.

Hypertrophied

Excessively developed.

Ichneumonidae

A family of hymenopterous insects, the members of which lay their eggs in the bodies or eggs of other insects.

Imago

The perfect (generally winged) reproductive state of an insect.

Indigenes

The aboriginal animal or vegetable inhabitants of a country or region.

Inflorescence

The mode of arrangement of the flowers of plants.

Infusoria

A class of microscopic animalcules, so called from their having originally been observed in infusions of vegetable matters. They consist of a gelatinous material enclosed in a delicate membrane, the whole or part of which is furnished with short vibrating hairs (called cilia), by means of which the animalcules swim through the water or convey the minute particles of their food to the orifice of the mouth.

Insectivorous

Feeding on insects.

Invertebrata
Invertebrate Animals

Those animals which do not possess a backbone or spinal column.

Lacunae

Spaces left among the tissues in some of the lower animals and serving in place of vessels for the circulation of the fluids of the body.

Lamellated

Furnished with lamellae or little plates.

Larva

(pl. Larvae): The first condition of an insect at its issuing from the egg, when it is usually in the form of a grub, caterpillar, or maggot.

Larynx

The upper part of the windpipe opening into the gullet.

Laurentian

A group of greatly altered and very ancient rocks, which is greatly developed along the course of the St. Laurence, whence the name. It is in these that the earliest known traces of organic bodies have been found.

Leguminosae

An order of plants represented by the common peas and beans, having an irregular flower in which one petal stands up like a wing, and the stamens and pistil are enclosed in a sheath formed by two other petals. The fruit is a pod (or legume).

Lemuridae

A group of four-handed animals, distinct from the monkeys and approaching the insectivorous quadrupeds in some of their characters and habits. Its members have the nostrils curved or twisted, and a claw instead of a nail upon the first finger of the hind hands.

Lepidoptera

An order of insects, characterised by the possession of a spiral proboscis, and of four large more or less scaly wings. It includes the well-known butterflies and moths.

Littoral

Inhabiting the seashore.

Loess

A marly deposit of recent (Post-Tertiary) date, which occupies a great part of the valley of the Rhine.

Malacostraca

The higher division of the Crustacea, including the ordinary crabs, lobsters, shrimps, etc., together with the woodlice and sand-hoppers.

Mammalia

The highest class of animals, including the ordinary hairy quadrupeds, the whales and man, and characterised by the production of living young which are nourished after birth by milk from the teats (Mammae, Mammary Glands) of the mother. A striking difference in embryonic development has led to the division of this class into two great groups; in one of these, when the embryo has attained a certain stage, a vascular connection, called the Placenta, is formed between the embryo and the mother; in the other this is wanting, and the young are produced in a very incomplete state. The former, including the greater part of the class, are called Placental Mammals; the latter, or Aplacental Mammals, include the Marsupials and Monotremes (Ornithorhynchus).

Mammiferous

Having mammae or teats (see Mammalia).

Mandibles

in insects, the first or uppermost pair of jaws, which are generally solid, horny, biting organs. In birds the term is applied to both jaws with their horny coverings. In quadrupeds the mandible is properly the lower jaw.

Marsupials

An order of Mammalia in which the young are born in a very incomplete state of development, and carried by the mother, while sucking, in a ventral pouch (marsupium), such as the kangaroos, opossums, etc. (see Mammalia).

Maxillae

in insects, the second or lower pair of jaws, which are composed of several joints and furnished with peculiar jointed appendages called palpi, or feelers.

Melanism

The opposite of albinism; an undue development of colouring material in the skin and its appendages.

Metamorphic Rocks

Sedimentary rocks which have undergone alteration, generally by the action of heat, subsequently to their deposition and consolidation.

Mollusca

One of the great divisions of the animal kingdom, including those animals which have a soft body, usually furnished with a shell, and in which the nervous ganglia, or centres, present no definite general arrangement. They are generally known under the denomination of “shellfish;” the cuttlefish, and the common snails, whelks, oysters, mussels, and cockles, may serve as examples of them.

Monocotyledons
Monocotyledonous Plants

Plants in which the seed sends up only a single seed-leaf (or cotyledon); characterised by the absence of consecutive layers of wood in the stem (endogenous growth), by the veins of the leaves being generally straight, and by the parts of the flowers being generally in multiples of three. (Examples, grasses, lilies, orchids, palms, etc.)

Moraines

The accumulations of fragments of rock brought down by glaciers.

Morphology

The law of form or structure independent of function.

Mysis

-Stage: A stage in the development of certain crustaceans (prawns), in which they closely resemble the adults of a genus (Mysis) belonging to a slightly lower group.

Nascent

Commencing development.

Natatory

Adapted for the purpose of swimming.

Nauplius-Form

The earliest stage in the development of many Crustacea, especially belonging to the lower groups. In this stage the animal has a short body, with indistinct indications of a division into segments, and three pairs of fringed limbs. This form of the common freshwater Cyclops was described as a distinct genus under the name of Nauplius.

Neuration

The arrangement of the veins or nervures in the wings of insects.

Neuters

Imperfectly developed females of certain social insects (such as ants and bees), which perform all the labours of the community. Hence, they are also called Workers.

Nictitating Membrane

A semitransparent membrane, which can be drawn across the eye in birds and reptiles, either to moderate the effects of a strong light or to sweep particles of dust, etc., from the surface of the eye.

Ocelli

The simple eyes or stemmata of insects, usually situated on the crown of the head between the great compound eyes.

Oesophagus

The gullet.

Oolitic

A great series of secondary rocks, so called from the texture of some of its members, which appear to be made up of a mass of small Egg-Like calcareous bodies.

Operculum

A calcareous plate employed by many Molluscae to close the aperture of their shell. The Opercular Valves of Cirripedes are those which close the aperture of the shell.

Orbit

The bony cavity for the reception of the eye.

Organism

An organised being, whether plant or animal.

Orthospermous

A term applied to those fruits of the Umbelliferae which have the seed straight.

Osculant

Forms or groups apparently intermediate between and connecting other groups are said to be osculant.

Ova

Eggs.

Ovarium
Ovary

(In plants): The lower part of the pistil or female organ of the flower, containing the ovules or incipient seeds; by growth after the other organs of the flower have fallen, it usually becomes converted into the fruit.

Ovigerous

Egg-bearing.

Ovules

(of plants): The seeds in the earliest condition.

Pachyderms

A group of Mammalia, so called from their thick skins, and including the elephant, rhinoceros, hippopotamus, etc.

Palaeozoic

The oldest system of fossiliferous rocks.

Palpi

Jointed appendages to some of the organs of the mouth in insects and Crustacea.

Papilionaceae

An order of plants (see Leguminosae). The flowers of these plants are called Papilionaceous, or butterfly-like, from the fancied resemblance of the expanded superior petals to the wings of a butterfly.

Parasite

An animal or plant living upon or in, and at the expense of, another organism.

Parthenogenesis

The production of living organisms from unimpregnated eggs or seeds.

Pedunculated

Supported upon a stem or stalk. The pedunculated oak has its acorns borne upon a footstool.

Peloria
Pelorism

The appearance of regularity of structure in the flowers of plants which normally bear irregular flowers.

Pelvis

The bony arch to which the hind limbs of vertebrate animals are articulated.

Petals

The leaves of the corolla, or second circle of organs in a flower. They are usually of delicate texture and brightly coloured.

Phyllodineous

Having flattened, leaf-like twigs or leafstalks instead of true leaves.

Pigment

The colouring material produced generally in the superficial parts of animals. The cells secreting it are called Pigment-Cells.

Pinnate

Bearing leaflets on each side of a central stalk.

Pistils

The female organs of a flower, which occupy a position in the centre of the other floral organs. The pistil is generally divisible into the ovary or germen, the style and the stigma.

Placentalia, Placentata

Or Placental Mammals. See Mammalia.

Plantigrades

Quadrupeds which walk upon the whole sole of the foot, like the bears.

Plastic

Readily capable of change.

Pleistocene Period

The latest portion of the Tertiary epoch.

Plumule

(in plants): The minute bud between the seed-leaves of newly-germinated plants.

Plutonic Rocks

Rocks supposed to have been produced by igneous action in the depths of the earth.

Pollen

The male element in flowering plants; usually a fine dust produced by the anthers, which, by contact with the stigma effects the fecundation of the seeds. This impregnation is brought about by means of tubes (Pollen-Tubes) which issue from the pollen-grains adhering to the stigma, and penetrate through the tissues until they reach the ovary.

Polyandrous

(flowers): Flowers having many stamens.

Polygamous Plants

Plants in which some flowers are unisexual and others hermaphrodite. The unisexual (male and female) flowers, may be on the same or on different plants.

Polymorphic

Presenting many forms.

Polyzoary

The common structure formed by the cells of the Polyzoa, such as the well-known seamats.

Prehensile

Capable of grasping.

Prepotent

Having a superiority of power.

Primaries

The feathers forming the tip of the wing of a bird, and inserted upon that part which represents the hand of man.

Processes

Projecting portions of bones, usually for the attachment of muscles, ligaments, etc.

Propolis

A resinous material collected by the hivebees from the opening buds of various trees.

Protean

Exceedingly variable.

Protozoa

The lowest great division of the animal kingdom. These animals are composed of a gelatinous material, and show scarcely any trace of distinct organs. The Infusoria, Foraminifera, and sponges, with some other forms, belong to this division.

Pupa

(pl. Pupae): The second stage in the development of an insect, from which it emerges in the perfect (winged) reproductive form. In most insects the Pupal Stage is passed in perfect repose. The Chrysalis is the pupal state of butterflies.

Radicle

The minute root of an embryo plant.

Ramus

One half of the lower jaw in the Mammalia. The portion which rises to articulate with the skull is called the Ascending Ramus.

Range

The extent of country over which a plant or animal is naturally spread. Range in Time expresses the distribution of a species or group through the fossiliferous beds of the earth’s crust.

Retina

The delicate inner coat of the eye, formed by nervous filaments spreading from the optic nerve, and serving for the perception of the impressions produced by light.

Retrogression

Backward development. When an animal, as it approaches maturity, becomes less perfectly organised than might be expected from its early stages and known relationships, it is said to undergo a Retrograde Development or Metamorphosis.

Rhizopods

A class of lowly organised animals (Protozoa), having a gelatinous body, the surface of which can be protruded in the form of root-like processes or filaments, which serve for locomotion and the prehension of food. The most important order is that of the Foraminifera.

Rodents

The gnawing Mammalia, such as the rats, rabbits, and squirrels. They are especially characterised by the possession of a single pair of chisel-like cutting teeth in each jaw, between which and the grinding teeth there is a great gap.

Rubus

The bramble genus.

Rudimentary

Very imperfectly developed.

Ruminants

The group of quadrupeds which ruminate or chew the cud, such as oxen, sheep, and deer. They have divided hoofs, and are destitute of front teeth in the upper jaw.

Sacral

Belonging to the sacrum, or the bone composed usually of two or more united vertebrae to which the sides of the pelvis in vertebrate animals are attached.

Sarcode

The gelatinous material of which the bodies of the lowest animals (Protozoa) are composed.

Scutellae

The horny plates with which the feet of birds are generally more or less covered, especially in front.

Sedimentary Formations

Rocks deposited as sediments from water.

Segments

The transverse rings of which the body of an articulate animal or annelid is composed.

Sepals

The leaves or segments of the calyx, or outermost envelope of an ordinary flower. They are usually green, but sometimes brightly coloured.

Serratures

Teeth like those of a saw.

Sessile

Not supported on a stem or footstalk.

Silurian System

A very ancient system of fossiliferous rocks belonging to the earlier part of the Palaeozoic series.

Specialisation

The setting apart of a particular organ for the performance of a particular function.

Spinal Cord

The central portion of the nervous system in the Vertebrata, which descends from the brain through the arches of the vertebrae, and gives off nearly all the nerves to the various organs of the body.

Stamens

The male organs of flowering plants, standing in a circle within the petals. They usually consist of a filament and an anther, the anther being the essential part in which the pollen, or fecundating dust, is formed.

Sternum

The breastbone.

Stigma

The apical portion of the pistil in flowering plants.

Stipules

Small leafy organs placed at the base of the footstalks of the leaves in many plants.

Style

The middle portion of the perfect pistil, which rises like a column from the ovary and supports the stigma at its summit.

Subcutaneous

Situated beneath the skin.

Suctorial

Adapted for sucking.

Sutures

(in the skull): The lines of junction of the bones of which the skull is composed.

Tarsus

(pl. Tarsi): The jointed feet of articulate animals, such as insects.

Teleostean Fishes

Fishes of the kind familiar to us in the present day, having the skeleton usually completely ossified and the scales horny.

Tentacula
Tentacles

Delicate fleshy organs of prehension or touch possessed by many of the lower animals.

Tertiary

The latest geological epoch, immediately preceding the establishment of the present order of things.

Trachea

The windpipe or passage for the admission of air to the lungs.

Tridactyle

Three-fingered, or composed of three movable parts attached to a common base.

Trilobites

A peculiar group of extinct crustaceans, somewhat resembling the woodlice in external form, and, like some of them, capable of rolling themselves up into a ball. Their remains are found only in the Palaeozoic rocks, and most abundantly in those of Silurian age.

Trimorphic

Presenting three distinct forms.

Umbelliferae

An order of plants in which the flowers, which contain five stamens and a pistil with two styles, are supported upon footstalks which spring from the top of the flower stem and spread out like the wires of an umbrella, so as to bring all the flowers in the same head (Umbel) nearly to the same level. (Examples, parsley and carrot.)

Ungulata

Hoofed quadrupeds.

Unicellular

Consisting of a single cell.

Vascular

Containing blood-vessels.

Vermiform

Like a worm.

Vertebrata
Vertebrate Animals

The highest division of the animal kingdom, so called from the presence in most cases of a backbone composed of numerous joints or Vertebrae, which constitutes the centre of the skeleton and at the same time supports and protects the central parts of the nervous system.

Whorls

The circles or spiral lines in which the parts of plants are arranged upon the axis of growth.

Workers

See neuters.

Zoea-Stage

The earliest stage in the development of many of the higher Crustacea, so called from the name of Zoea applied to these young animals when they were supposed to constitute a peculiar genus.

Zooids

In many of the lower animals (such as the Corals, Medusae, etc.) reproduction takes place in two ways, namely, by means of eggs and by a process of budding with or without separation from the parent of the product of the latter, which is often very different from that of the egg. The individuality of the species is represented by the whole of the form produced between two sexual reproductions; and these forms, which are apparently individual animals, have been called Zooide.